In August 1347, a decade into the Hundred Years
War, the port city of Calais surrendered to King
Edward III of England after an eleven-month siege.
As the mayor of Calais and five of his fellow
townsmen surrendered the city’s keys to Edward,
the King ordered their execution as punishment for
their refusal to submit. While Edward refused the
pleas of close friends to spare them, his pregnant
queen Philippa of Hainault sank to her knees.
She begged of her husband, “that for the Son of
the Holy Mary and for the love of me, you shall
wish to have mercy on these six men”. Edward,
one of England’s greatest warrior kings, was moved
by his wife’s intervention and relented. The tale
of the townsmen or burghers of Calais is regarded
as a vivid demonstration of the power of medieval
queenship. However, Philippa’s power and influence
as Queen of England was not confined to this
single spectacle. She effectively deputised for
Edward as a political and military leader while he
was away on campaign, and her dynastic connections
on the continent made her a useful diplomat.
Philippa and Edward were happily married and she
performed her dynastic role effectively by having
several surviving sons to secure the future
of the House of Plantagenet. Nevertheless,
Philippa’s childbearing prowess
would also set the stage for the
bitter internecine struggles which would
divide the English realm in the century
after her death. This is the story of
Philippa of Hainault, Queen of England.
The woman known to history as Philippa of Hainault
was born in Valenciennes in the County of Hainaut,
on the western borderlands of the Holy Roman
Empire. While the historical county gives its
name to the modern-day Belgian province of
Hainaut, Philippa’s hometown of Valenciennes
has been part of France since the 17th century.
While her accepted date of birth is 24 June 1314,
this is unlikely. The Queen was “almost fourteen
years old” at her wedding in January 1328,
according to the chronicler Jean Froissart who
was patronised by Philippa in the 1360s. In 1319,
King Edward II of England dispatched the Bishop
of Exeter, Walter Stapledon, to the court
at Hainaut to consider the suitability of the
Count’s daughters as a bride for Prince Edward,
the future Edward III. He left a detailed
account of one of the Count’s daughters who
would be “nine years on St John’s day next
to come”. This would place Philippa’s date
of birth on 24 June 1310 or 1311. While this
account was later understood to have been a
description of Philippa as she later married
Edward, modern scholarship indicates that
Stapledon was referring to Philippa’s elder sister
Margarethe. On the basis of Froissart’s account,
Philippa’s biographer Kathryn Warner argues that
she was born between January and March 1314.
Philippa’s father Count William I of Hainault was
a member of the House of Avesnes, whose ancestral
estates were in the village of Avesnes-sur-Helpe
in northern France. In addition to counties of
Hainault and Avesnes, William also ruled over the
counties of Holland and Zeeland and spent much
of his life at war with the Count of Flanders. In
1305 he married Joan of Valois, the granddaughter
of King Philip III of France. When the male line
of the House of Capet was extinguished in 1328,
Joan’s brother became King Philip VI of France,
asserting his claims over those of his distant
cousin Edward III of England. The rival claims
of Philippa’s uncle and husband to the kingdom
of France would trigger an Anglo-French conflict
which would last for more than a century.
Philippa grew up in a large family with eight or
nine full siblings, of whom around half survived
into adulthood. Her father Count William also
had at least eight illegitimate children whom
he acknowledged as his own and may have brought
up in his household. Count William ruled over a
collection of small but wealthy counties in the
Low Countries who owed their prosperity to their
commercial relationship with England across the
North Sea. It was no surprise that King Edward II
of England had sought the hand of one of William’s
daughters for his son and heir in the late 1310s.
Bishop Stapelton’s detailed account of William’s
daughter in 1319 noted that the girl was “brown
of skin all over, much like her father.” The
Bishop’s description of the Hainault girl has
encouraged the notion that Philippa had African
ancestry, and she was controversially included
in the 100 Great Black Britons project in
2003. While Philippa’s maternal ancestors
included not only southern Europeans of darker
complexion but also a chieftain of the Cumans,
a nomadic Turkic people from central Asia, none
of this indicates African ancestry. It also does
not account for the apparent dark skin of Count
William, who was exclusively of northern European
descent. While it remains unclear what Stapleton
meant by describing the Count of Hainault and
his daughter having brown skin all over,
Kathryn Warner observes that there is no
source during Philippa’s queenship that remarks
on her appearance being unconventional.
Philippa grew up at a time of great uncertainty
in western European politics. Medieval aristocrats
travelled between their estates and Philippa’s
childhood was split between Valenciennes and
her father’s estates in Holland. Philippa
spoke French and Flemish and was likely
acquainted with the Arthurian romances and the
religious texts in her father’s small library.
In 1323, Count William made peace with the Count
of Flanders by giving up his claim to Flanders
in exchange for formal recognition as Count of
Zeeland. This gave William the opportunity to
arrange advantageous marriages for his daughters.
Philippa likely joined her family at the double
wedding ceremony in Cologne in February 1324,
where her elder sisters Margaret and Joanna
were married to Ludwig IV of Bavaria and Wilhelm
of Jülich respectively. The 42-year-old Ludwig
was one of Europe’s most powerful men. He had
recently defeated his cousin and rival, Frederick
of Austria, consolidating his claim as King of
Germany. Wilhelm of Jülich was also heir to the
county of Jülich, which straddled the present-day
borders of Germany and the Netherlands. Philippa
may have attended the wedding of her mother’s
cousins King Charles IV of France and Joan of
Evreux in Paris on 5 July 1324. The youngest of
King Philip IV’s three sons, Charles had come to
the throne after his elder brothers died without
heirs. He was therefore desperate for a son to
secure his lineage. In December 1325, Philippa
accompanied her mother to Paris to visit her
dying grandfather Charles of Valois. During her
stay at the French capital, Philippa likely met
Edward of Windsor, the heir to the English throne,
and his mother Queen Isabella, who was the sister
of the King of France. Isabella had travelled to
France to broker a peace agreement between her
husband and her brother but was in no hurry to
return home. She was appalled by the influence
of Edward II’s courtier and rumoured lover, Hugh
Despenser the Younger. Hugh Despenser used his
favoured position to appropriate the lands of
leading aristocrats and even the queen herself.
In late 1325, Isabella issued an ultimatum
and declared that she would remain in
France until Edward dismissed Despenser.
The young Philippa was to be a major player in
the scandal that embarrassed the English court.
Prince Edward had accompanied his mother to France
in order to pay homage to the King of France for
the duchy of Aquitaine, which was now reduced to
the region of Gascony. Although Edward was
already betrothed to a Spanish princess,
Isabella may have been in correspondence with
the Hainault court about the prospect of a union
between Edward and Philippa even before the latter
arrived in Paris with her mother. An unofficial
arrangement appears to have been made in December
1325 when Joan and Philippa were in France,
suggesting that Philippa met her future husband
for the first time. The pair may have met on
a second occasion at Joan of Evreux’s coronation
as Queen of France in May 1326, though Philippa’s
attendance is uncertain. The marital negotiations
could not have taken place without the knowledge
of Philippa’s father Count William. It was he
alone who could provide the men and ships for an
invasion of England and he had been on poor terms
with King Edward since the early 1320s. Relations
between the two rulers deteriorated over pirate
raids in the North Sea. In addition, the prospect
of having the heir to the English throne as his
son-in-law was attractive enough to encourage
him to join the rebellion against the anointed
sovereign of England. In late 1325, Isabella
gained another powerful ally in Roger Mortimer, an
English nobleman who had escaped from the Tower of
London after an unsuccessful rebellion to remove
Hugh Despenser. Philippa may have met Mortimer in
early 1326 while he was in Hainault to discuss
invasion plans with Count William. Isabella and
Edward visited the Hainault court in the summer,
and on 27 August Edward and Philippa were formally
betrothed in the town of Mons. Even before
receiving news of the unsanctioned engagement,
King Edward wrote to his son demanding he
return to England. If the 13-year-old prince
had even wished to do so, he was an effective
prisoner of his mother and had little choice.
On 24 September 1326, Isabella and Mortimer
launched their successful invasion of England.
Exactly two months later Hugh Despenser was
executed in gruesome fashion. As the pair
took effective control of the kingdom, the
fate of Edward II remained open to question.
In January 1327, Edward was forced to abdicate
the throne in favour of his teenage son, who was
crowned King Edward III on 1 February 1327. The
deposed monarch, known as Edward of Caernarvon,
after his birthplace in Wales, lived in relative
comfort at Berkeley Castle in Gloucestershire
until his mysterious death in September 1327.
Edward III later announced that his father had
been murdered, and the late king’s fondness
for male companionship inspired the apocryphal
tale that a red-hot poker had caused his demise.
Meanwhile, Philippa spent much of 1327 preparing
for her nuptials with the newly enthroned Edward
III. Since Edward and Philippa were cousins, their
proposed marriage required a papal dispensation,
which was granted in August by Pope John XXII in
Avignon. Philippa landed in Dover in December
1327, a few days before Edward II’s funeral
at Gloucester. She and Edward III were married in
York on 25 January 1328, the first anniversary of
the King’s accession to the throne a year earlier.
Philippa of Hainault, just shy of her 14th
birthday, was now England’s queen consort. Despite
this, she had little influence in a court which
remained under the control of her mother-in-law
Isabella and her chief counsellor, Roger Mortimer.
Although the new regime had eliminated the hated
Despenser, Mortimer and Isabella were no less
corrupt. For Edward III, the companionship of his
young wife would have been a welcome respite from
his overbearing mother and her presumed lover.
Philippa’s wedding was but one of three major
events in two weeks which involved the Hainault
family and its close relatives. On 17 January
1328, Philippa’s brother-in-law Ludwig of Bavaria
was crowned Holy Roman Emperor in Rome. Since Pope
John XXII in Avignon was Ludwig’s enemy and
had excommunicated him, Ludwig was crowned by
a cardinal and set up an antipope of his own. A
week after the wedding, King Charles IV of France
died aged 33 on 1 February 1328, leaving behind
two daughters and a pregnant wife. If Joan of
Evreux were to give birth to a boy, the baby would
become King of France at the moment of his birth.
In the event, Joan gave birth to a daughter on 1
April, and with the extinction of the male line
of King Philip IV, the closest claimant through
the female line was King Edward III of England,
Philip’s grandson via Queen Isabella. Although
Edward had the strongest claim, French elites
could never countenance the prospect of the King
of England becoming their own sovereign. Instead,
they enthroned Philippa’s maternal uncle Philip of
Valois, who became King Philip VI on 1 April 1328
and was crowned in Reims on 29 May 1328. Isabella
was infuriated by Philip’s accession, but Edward
had no choice but to pay fealty to Philip in
1329 to secure his French domains of Ponthieu and
Aquitaine. Meanwhile, Philippa was only granted
a modest annual allowance in April 1329 and
remained under the shadow of her mother-in-law.
King Edward himself was desperate to exercise
his royal power. In October 1328, Roger Mortimer
became earl of March, giving him control of the
borderlands of England and Wales. This encouraged
a rebellion by the king’s great-uncle Henry,
earl of Lancaster, which was defeated
by Mortimer’s forces in January 1329.
While the failure of Lancaster’s rebellion
temporarily strengthened Mortimer’s position,
Edward III was cultivating his own supporters
behind the scenes. Meanwhile, rumours abounded
that the former Edward II was still alive in
Corfe Castle in Dorset. This prompted an active
campaign to liberate him and restore him to his
throne. Amid these uncertainties for the young
royal couple, Philippa became pregnant in autumn
1329. This forced Isabella to arrange Philippa’s
coronation as Queen of England on 18 February
1330 and to grant her the lordship of Glamorgan
in South Wales, which had been confiscated from
Hugh Despenser’s widow. Unbeknownst to the royal
family, the King’s uncle Edmund, Earl of Kent, was
plotting with William Melton, Archbishop of York,
to free Edward II and restore him to power.
Kent’s swift arrest and execution in March
1330 is an indication that the former King was
still alive and remained a threat to the regime.
Mortimer and Isabella were present for the birth
of Philippa’s son Edward on 15 June 1330 at
Woodstock Palace in Oxfordshire. While Edward is
known to history as the Black Prince, during his
lifetime he was known as Edward of Woodstock. His
birth strengthened King Edward’s hand, and on 19
October 1330 the King and a group of loyal knights
broke into Isabella’s chamber at Nottingham Castle
while she was meeting with Mortimer and their
allies. Mortimer was arrested and was taken
to the Tower of London before being executed for
regicide on 29 November 1330. Isabella was granted
an allowance of £3,000 a year and remained at
liberty while being kept at a distance from court.
The young King was keen to bring harmony to his
realm and restored the estates of the Despensers,
Henry of Lancaster, and the family of
the late earl of Kent. Decades later,
Edward would also rehabilitate the Mortimer family
and bring them back into royal favour.
With Edward now in control of his kingdom,
Philippa assumed a more prominent role at
the glamorous court festivities. She was given
a host of estates which increased her income to
£4,000 a year, although this was not enough to
meet her household expenses. While she received
additional sums from Edward’s Exchequer, her debts
continued to pile ever higher. Notwithstanding
their cost, the young royal couple’s lavish court
entertainments inspired a sense of optimism after
a decade of disorder. King Edward maintained
close relations with his in-laws, and in early
1331 Count William of Hainault went to France
to mediate on disagreements between England
and France. A few months later, Philippa’s mother,
Joan of Valois, visited England with her daughter
Joanna and her son-in-law Count Wilhelm of Jülich.
They likely attended the series of jousting
tournaments which were held in the summer of 1331.
In September, Philippa was attending a joust at
Cheapside in London when the ladies’ grandstand
collapsed. While the Queen’s coronet was damaged,
she persuaded her husband not to punish the
carpenters, and the tournament continued the
following morning after overnight repairs. In
late spring 1332, Philippa gave birth to her
second child, a daughter named Isabella. While
the royal couple was staying at Knaresborough
Castle in April 1333, Philippa obtained a pardon
for a pregnant woman named Agnes of Scarborough,
who had been sentenced to hanging for theft.
Philippa would gain a reputation for interceding
on behalf of pregnant or young women facing
execution. Around this time, Philippa began her
third pregnancy and spent her first trimester
at Bamburgh Castle while the King went to war
with King David II of Scotland, the infant son of
Robert the Bruce and Edward’s own brother-in-law.
After recapturing the port of Berwick-upon-Tweed,
Edward defeated a Scottish army at the Battle
of Halidon Hill on 18 July 1333. This was an
early demonstration of his military prowess.
In January 1334 Philippa gave birth to her second
daughter, whom she named Joan after her mother. As
Edward continued his war in Scotland, Philippa’s
brother-in-law Count Wilhelm of Jülich joined
Edward’s campaign in July and August 1335. Edward
also received the support of Robert of Artois,
who was married to the namesake half-sister of
Philippa’s mother Joan of Valois. Robert fled
into exile after attempting to claim the county
of Artois by forging his father’s will. In the
meantime, his wife Joan was imprisoned by her
half-brother King Philip of France. Meanwhile,
Edward aimed to strengthen his dynastic links
to the continent by arranging the marriage of
his newborn daughter Joan with Frederick, the son
of Duke Otto of Austria. As the sister-in-law of
the Holy Roman Emperor, Philippa could influence
the German princes on the matter. The royal couple
remained in northern England over Christmas 1335,
and Philippa became pregnant again in April 1336.
While Edward resumed his Scottish campaign in the
summer, Philippa presided over a royal council
on 2 September 1336 to consider the situation in
Scotland, where Edward was attempting to install
the nobleman Edward Balliol on the Scottish
throne in return for cessions of land. During
the campaign, King Edward’s only brother John of
Eltham, the earl of Cornwall, died of a fever at
the age of 20. The royal bereavements continued
into early 1337, after Philippa gave birth to a
short-lived son named William. A few months later,
Philippa’s father Count William of Hainault died
on 7 June 1337. He was succeeded by his only
surviving son, Count William II of Hainault.
The fateful year of 1337 also witnessed the start
of the conflict between England and France known
as the Hundred Years War. This began when Philip
VI confiscated the duchy of Aquitaine from Edward
III in response to the latter’s refusal to give
up the fugitive Robert of Artois. In response,
Edward revived his claim to the whole of France
and declared war on Philip. Between July 1338
and November 1340, Edward was frequently on the
continent seeking allies. Philippa accompanied
her husband on these diplomatic missions as
personal companion, trusted political advisor,
and a conduit to her powerful relatives on the
continent. Not long after their arrival in Antwerp
in July 1338, the royal couple’s lodgings caught
fire and they had to escape in their nightclothes.
Philippa remained in Antwerp to give birth
to her second surviving son in November,
who was given the unusual name of Lionel after
the Arthurian knight. During the latter stages of
the Queen’s pregnancy, Edward sailed up the Rhine
with his brother-in-law Wilhelm of Jülich, whom he
created earl of Cambridge. At the city of Cologne,
where Wilhelm’s younger brother was archbishop,
the King worshiped at the shrine of the Three
Kings in the city’s cathedral. In September,
Edward met with Ludwig of Bavaria and senior
imperial princes at Koblenz, where he obtained
an alliance against France and an appointment
as a vicar of the Holy Roman Emperor. During
Edward’s stay in Koblenz, he met a man called
“William le Galeys” or William the Welshman,
who claimed to be the king’s father. The so-called
Fieschi letter, written by a papal notary to King
Edward III in around 1337, claimed that the
deposed Edward II had escaped from Berkeley
Castle. From there, he had fled to the continent
before establishing himself in northern Italy.
Royal accounts suggest that this William
could have accompanied the King to Antwerp,
where he may have met Philippa. After becoming
pregnant for the sixth time in late spring 1339,
Philippa spent the winter at Louvain. There she
met her brother Count William II and her mother
Joan, who had retired to Fontenelle abbey near
Valenciennes after the death of her husband.
On 26 January 1340, the royal family arrived
in the Flemish town of Ghent, where Edward III
was officially proclaimed King of France. On 6
March 1340, Philippa gave birth to her son John,
known to history as John of Gaunt. Three months
later, King Edward III won a great naval victory
over the French at the Battle of Sluys on 24
June 1340. In September, while the English
were besieging the French at Tournai, Edward
met Joan of Valois, who successfully brokered
an Anglo-French truce. This enabled Edward and
Philippa to return to England in November 1340
during the early stages of the Queen’s seventh
pregnancy. In January 1341, Philippa’s chaplain
Robert de Eglesfield founded a new college at
the University of Oxford named Queen’s Hall in
her honour, which survives as Queen’s College.
In addition to the Oxford college, Philippa also
patronised several other religious houses and
hospitals around the country. On 5 June 1341,
Philippa gave birth to her son Edmund at the royal
palace of Langley in Hertfordshire. The birth of
three healthy sons in less than three years helped
Edward III secure his line of succession but would
become a source of instability to the kingdom
by the end of the century. A few weeks earlier,
the two-year-old Lionel of Antwerp
was betrothed to the eight-year-old
Elizabeth de Burgh, who stood to inherit her
family’s vast estates in Ireland.
In late 1341, King Edward returned to lead a
campaign in Scotland. According to the French
chronicler Jean le Bel, the King developed an
infatuation for the countess of Salisbury after
rescuing her from a besieged castle. When she
resisted his advances, he violently assaulted her
and left her unconscious. Most historians reject
le Bel’s account since the count of Salisbury,
William Montacute, was one of the King’s closest
friends. Kathryn Warner notes that le Bel referred
to the countess as Alice rather than Catherine,
and may have confused her for Alice of Norfolk,
who was brutally beaten to death in 1351
by her husband Edward Montacute, William’s
younger brother. After returning to England, in
January 1342 Edward granted his son John of Gaunt
the earldom of Richmond in Yorkshire. This had
previously belonged to Duke John III of Brittany,
whose death in April 1341 caused a succession
crisis in the duchy that would reignite the
Anglo-French conflict. In February, Philippa
joined Edward at a great tournament to celebrate
their son Lionel’s betrothal to Elizabeth de
Burgh. By then she was heavily pregnant with
her daughter Blanche, who died shortly after
her birth in March. In late spring and summer,
Philippa’s brother Count William II visited
England to participate in a series of tournaments
hosted by the King. These included the joust in
August 1342 which brought together the cream of
English nobility, its purpose being to celebrate
the wedding of Lionel of Antwerp and Elizabeth
de Burgh. Although both were still children,
the King may have decided to formalise the
union to protect Elizabeth from abduction,
a fate that several wealthy heiresses had
suffered. Philippa was granted custody of her
daughter-in-law’s estates in Ireland until she
attained her majority. Elizabeth joined her
husband Lionel and the younger royal children
in the joint household attached to the Queen.
In September 1342, Edward III intervened in the
War of the Breton succession by sending an army
to support the claim of John of Montfort. While
Edward himself soon left to take command, his
efforts were unsuccessful and the renegade Robert
of Artois was killed in action in November. Edward
of Woodstock had been formally appointed regent in
his father’s absence, though Queen Philippa
was entrusted with ensuring that the King’s
instructions to bury Robert at Blackfriars church
were carried out. In May 1343, after returning to
England, the King made his son Edward the Prince
of Wales. Edward III held another magnificent
tournament of 300 knights at Windsor in January
1344, though it was at this event that his close
friend, the Count of Salisbury, was mortally
injured. Around this time, Dowager Queen Isabella
joined Edward and Philippa on a hunting trip, an
indication of the King’s closer relations with his
mother. Meanwhile, Philippa became pregnant with
her daughter Mary who was born in October 1344
at Bishop’s Waltham in Hampshire. In 1344, King
Edward made serious efforts to strengthen his
alliance with his cousin Duke Jan III of Brabant
by proposing the marriage of his eldest children
to those of the Duke. These efforts were abandoned
after Edward failed to secure papal dispensation
for the union of two pairs of cousins. In June
1345, the King turned his attention to the Iberian
Peninsula and proposed marrying the five-year-old
John of Gaunt to Queen Maria of Castile’s younger
sister Eleanor of Portugal, then aged 17. The
following month, Edward proposed the union of his
eldest daughter Isabella of Woodstock and Infante
Pedro, the son of King Alfonso XI of Castile. As
the negotiations carried on into November,
Edward III proposed the 15-year-old Prince
of Wales as a more suitable match for Eleanor.
On 26 September 1345, Philippa’s younger brother
Count William II of Hainault was killed
while fighting rebels in Friesland. While
the 38-year-old William had two illegitimate
sons, he had no legitimate children with his
wife Johanna of Brabant. Under English law, the
property of a deceased landowner without a son was
divided among surviving daughters. Since William
had four surviving sisters, Edward III claimed
that Philippa had the right to inherit a quarter
of William’s lands. Under inheritance laws on
the continent, all of William’s possessions were
inherited by his eldest sister Empress Margaret.
The dispute over the Hainault inheritance led
to tensions between Edward and his ally Emperor
Ludwig. King Philip VI supported Margaret’s claim
on the grounds that the Hainault counties were
already part of the Holy Roman Empire, while the
alternative would strengthen his English enemy.
The situation was further complicated in summer
1346 when five of the seven imperial electors
voted to depose Ludwig as Holy Roman Emperor and
elect Charles of Luxembourg instead. Weeks after
his election, Charles and his blind father King
John of Bohemia joined the French army as Philip
VI prepared to respond to devastating raids across
Normandy by Edward III and the Prince of Wales in
July. What ensued was a devastating victory of
English longbowmen against the French knights at
the Battle of Crécy. The battle resulted in
the deaths of thousands of French noblemen,
including several of Queen Philippa’s kinsmen.
The heavily pregnant Queen was obliged to
remain in England and gave birth to her tenth
child, Margaret of Windsor, on 20 July 1346.
While her husband and son were on the continent,
a Scottish army invaded northern England. Three
Flemish chroniclers describe Philippa raising
an army and riding out to defeat the Scots
at the Battle of Neville’s Cross on 17 October,
during which King David II of Scotland fell into
English captivity. The tale of Philippa leading
the army at Neville’s Cross was repeated by the
Tudor historian Raphael Holinshed. It is also
the subject of a 1789 painting by Benjamin West,
commissioned by King George III for Windsor
Castle. While Kathryn Warner dismisses
Philippa’s presence at Neville’s Cross by citing
correspondence in her name from Edward’s siege
camp at Calais on 21 September and 23 October
1346, Jordan Michelle Schoonover argues that it
was not inconceivable that the Queen performed
this action. She could, he argues, have sailed
to Newcastle-upon-Tyne to supervise the war effort
against the Scots before returning to Calais after
the victory. While the seven-year-old Lionel of
Antwerp was officially named regent during Edward
III’s absence in France, Philippa would have been
in a position to act on his behalf. Around this
time, Philippa met her sister Margaret at Ypres to
mend their relations over the Hainault succession.
In March 1347, the English royal couple and their
daughter Isabella met Louis de Male who had become
Count of Flanders after his father’s death at
Crécy. While Louis agreed to marry Isabella
and recognise Edward as king of France, he
fled to the French court soon thereafter.
Calais’ surrender in August 1347 created the
conditions for Philippa’s famous intercession
to spare the burghers of Calais, whose anguish
was memorably depicted by the sculptor Auguste
Rodin in the late 19th century. However, Kathryn
Warner and Lisa Hilton highlight inconsistencies
in Froissart’s account, such as the fact that
Philippa could not have been heavily pregnant
as the chroniclers described. Even if Philippa’s
intercession did otherwise take place in public,
they argue that Edward had made up his mind
to spare the burghers. However, the Queen’s
intercession allowed him to do so in an apparently
spontaneous gesture of clemency while maintaining
a hard line against those who defied his will.
In October 1347, Philippa’s brother-in-law Ludwig
of Bavaria died at the age of 65. His death
secured the position of Charles of Luxembourg,
though in January 1348 Edward III received four
votes from German electors who hoped to install
him as an anti-king to Charles. After Edward
refused, Charles’ election was confirmed in 1349,
and in 1355 he was crowned as the Holy Roman
Emperor, Charles IV. As Philippa and Edward
returned to England in October 1347, the Queen
was pregnant for the eleventh time. A few weeks
before she gave birth to William of Windsor
in May 1348, the King formally instituted the
Order of the Garter on 23 April, St George’s
Day. Inspired by King Arthur’s round table,
Edward named 24 of his closest companions as
knights of the Garter with himself and the
Prince of Wales at the top of the list.
According to legend, Edward adopted the
garter after the Countess of Salisbury’s garter
slipped off her leg at a ball. The King picked
it up and proclaimed “Honi soit qui mal y pense”.
This, translated, means, “Shame on he who thinks
ill of it”. Historians believe that the tale
was invented in the 15th century after men
stopped wearing garters, and Lisa Hilton argues
that the order’s motto referred to his claim to
the French throne. The optimism of the English
court in early 1348 also reflected successful
marriage negotiations with Castile. In 1347, the
Castilians had agreed in principle to the marriage
of Eleanor of Portugal to Edward of Woodstock,
but the English envoys were significantly delayed
and upon their arrival, Eleanor had already
married King Pedro IV of Aragon. In late 1347,
Edward III succeeded in arranging the marriage
of his second daughter Joan to Infante Pedro,
the only legitimate son of King Alfonso XI of
Castile. The 14-year-old Joan left England in
the summer of 1348, but fell ill and died
in Gascony. She was one of millions who had
succumbed to the Black Death, the bubonic plague
that killed prince and pauper as it swept through
Europe. Around this time, Philippa and Edward
were also mourning the death of the newborn
William. Some sources indicate that the royal
couple also lost a son named Thomas of Windsor
to the plague. The historian Kathryn Warner,
however, argues that Thomas never existed and
was invented to reconcile the Flemish accounts
of Philippa being heavily pregnant at Calais.
In late February 1350, Alfonso XI of Spain
succumbed to the plague and was succeeded by
Pedro, who imprisoned and executed his father’s
lover Eleanor de Guzmán. This provoked a civil
war between King Pedro and his illegitimate
half-brother Enrique de Trastámara, who eventually
emerged victorious in 1369. Meanwhile, King
Edward was irritated by pirate attacks on English
shipping led by the Franco-Castilian nobleman
Carlos de la Cerda. On 29 August 1350, King
Edward III intercepted and defeated the Castilian
fleet at the Battle of Winchelsea off the Sussex
coast. Large numbers of enemy ships were captured
and sunk, although the English lost significant
numbers of men. The Prince of Wales and John
of Gaunt both participated in the battle, while
Queen Philippa anxiously observed proceedings from
shore. A few days earlier, Philippa’s uncle King
Philip VI of France died and was succeeded by his
son King John II. Her mother Joan of Valois died
less than two years later on 7 March 1352 in her
late fifties. Philippa herself was in her late
thirties and had been Queen of England for over
two decades. The Queen had not been pregnant since
the birth of the short-lived William of Windsor
in 1348, but on 7 January 1355 she gave birth to
a son named Thomas at Woodstock. Later that year,
Lionel of Antwerp and Elizabeth de Burgh gave
Philippa her first legitimate grandchild in August
1355, a girl named Philippa, after the Queen.
Meanwhile, the war against France gained
renewed intensity, and on 19 September
1356 the Black Prince won a great victory at
the Battle of Poitiers. Philippa’s cousin,
King John II of France, was captured and paraded
through the streets of London in May 1357.
The imprisoned King spent the remainder of his
life in relative comfort at Savoy Palace in London
and attended the celebrations of the Order of the
Garter in April 1358, when Philippa was appointed
the first Lady of the Garter. The event was
the last major public appearance of the Dowager
Queen Isabella, who died in August in her early
sixties. Not long afterwards, Philippa injured
her shoulder after falling from her horse while
hunting. In November Philippa and Edward attended
the wedding of their three-year-old granddaughter
Philippa with Edmund Mortimer. He was the son and
heir of Roger Mortimer, a knight of the Garter and
the namesake grandson of the man who had deposed
Edward II. The royal couple hurried to make
arrangements for their seven unmarried children,
and on 19 May 1359, John of Gaunt married Blanche
of Lancaster, whose father Henry of Grosmont was
the Duke of Lancaster and one of Edward’s most
accomplished military leaders. The same day,
the Queen’s youngest daughter Margaret of Windsor
married John Hastings, heir to the earldom of
Pembroke in South Wales and a maternal grandson
of the first Roger Mortimer. When King Edward
and his four eldest sons returned to campaign in
France in October, the Queen remained in England
with the pregnant Blanche of Lancaster, who gave
birth to a daughter on 31 March 1360. The girl was
named Philippa after her grandmother and would
later become Queen of Portugal. After Edward’s
return to England in May 1360, he combined
his household with the Queen’s in an effort to
take control of Philippa’s spiralling debts.
The royal marriages continued in spring 1361,
when the Prince of Wales married his recently
widowed cousin Joan of Kent. Since Joan was in
her thirties and had previously been bigamously
married to Thomas Holland and William Montacute,
2nd Earl of Salisbury, Philippa and Edward were
initially opposed to the marriage. However, they
gave their consent in the autumn. In the spring of
1361, Philippa’s daughter Mary of Waltham married
John de Montfort, the claimant to the duchy of
Brittany. While John would later take control of
Brittany, the 17-year-old Mary died in September
a few months after the wedding. Her younger sister
Margaret followed her to the grave a few weeks
later, leaving Isabella of Woodstock as Philippa’s
only surviving daughter. In June 1362, the Black
Prince was named prince of Aquitaine and crossed
the Channel to take over its government, never
to see his mother again. To mark his fiftieth
birthday in November 1362, the King named his
sons Lionel of Antwerp, John of Gaunt, and Edmund
of Langley the dukes of Clarence, Lancaster, and
Cambridge respectively. Although Philippa was not
yet 50, her health deteriorated rapidly after her
shoulder injury. While Edward III is unlikely to
have remained entirely faithful to Philippa during
their first three decades of marriage, there is
no record of the King fathering any illegitimate
children. The Queen’s illness led Edward to take
on Alice Perrers from the Queen’s household as his
permanent mistress. Alice, who was born in 1348,
gave Edward a son and two daughters between
1364 and 1366. Given her own incapacity,
Philippa may have given her blessing to the King’s
affair. Royal records show that the Queen was
still able to travel, albeit less frequently. In
January 1365, Philippa celebrated the news of the
birth of Edward of Angouléme, the first son of the
Black Prince and Joan of Kent. Six months later,
Philippa’s 33-year-old daughter Isabella of
Woodstock married Enguerrand de Coucy. He was
a French nobleman up to ten years her junior who
was made Earl of Bedford in 1366.
In January 1367, Philippa received news
that Edward and Joan had their second son,
named Richard of Bordeaux. Three months later,
John of Gaunt and Blanche of Lancaster had their
first son, Henry Bolingbroke. Philippa could not
have known at the time that the two boys would
become England’s next two kings, Richard II and
Henry IV. At the time of his son’s birth, John
of Gaunt was campaigning in Spain with his brother
Edward. Although the campaign had been successful,
the Black Prince fell seriously ill and remained
an invalid until his death in 1376. Queen Philippa
herself was approaching her end, but she lived to
learn of the demise of her 30-year-old son Lionel
of Antwerp, who died in Italy in October 1368
shortly after his marriage to his second wife,
Violante Visconti. The previous month, Philippa’s
daughter-in-law Blanche of Lancaster died at the
age of 26. In December, Philippa attempted to
broker the marriage of the widowed John of Gaunt
with Margaret of Flanders, the heiress to Flanders
and four French counties. She was too late,
as Count Louis of Flanders informed her that
Margaret was to marry Philip, the youngest brother
of King Charles V of France. King Charles was also
the Duke of Burgundy and the founder of one of the
most powerful dynasties of late medieval Europe.
The negotiations show that Philippa remained
politically active despite her poor health. On 22
June 1369, Philippa interceded on behalf of Alice
Marchant and Margaret Melbury, two pregnant
women who faced the death penalty for theft.
These were among her last items of business,
and she died on 15 August 1369, aged 55,
with her husband King Edward III and her youngest
son Thomas of Woodstock in attendance.
Philippa of Hainault was one of the
longest-serving queen consorts in
English history. Born into a small but
ambitious dynasty in the Low Countries,
Philippa was not only Queen of England but closely
related to the king of France and the Holy Roman
Emperor. In nearly four decades as Edward III’s
queen, she was almost always at her husband’s
side at home and abroad as a trusted advisor and
diplomat. While she struggled to keep control of
expenditures at her husband’s glamorous court,
the Flemish chroniclers show her as an effective
deputy for the King in political and military
affairs. Philippa’s tenure as queen witnessed the
early decades of the Hundred Years War, including
the great English victories at Crécy and Poitiers,
as well as the Black Death and further outbreaks
of plague. In an era of high mortality, Philippa
gave her husband twelve children and outlived
seven of them. While none of her sons ever became
King, her grandson Richard II succeeded to the
throne in June 1377 after the death of Edward III.
The Wars of the Roses that tore England
apart in the 15th century would be fought
between the descendants of her third son, John
of Gaunt and her fourth son, Edmund of Langley.
What do you think of Philippa of Hainault?
Was she one of the most effective queens
of medieval England, or was her influence
exaggerated by chroniclers close to her court?
Please let us know in the comment section and in
the meantime, thank you very much for watching.